Finding Aid for Mill Creek Research Council, Inc. Records 1960-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mill Creek Research Council, inc. records 1960-1988
Mill Creek Research Council, inc.
Citizen action group formed in 1964-1965 by Mrs. Virginia Denham to oppose the flooding of the Mill Creek area in Lima Township, Washtenaw County, Michigan, to improve sewage treatment for communities downstream on the Huron River. The organization also opposed creation of a Mill Creek Metropark by the Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority an developed the South Lima Township Historical District plan. Correspondence, environmental impact statements, administrative files, newsletters, newspaper articles, topical files, maps, and photographs.
85323 Bn 2
9 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Mill Creek Research Council record group (Donor no. 6266 ) was donated by the organization's board through its chairperson, Mrs. Virginia Denham, in July 1982 and October 1993 and by Mr. David Bacon (Donor no. 8527 ) in November 1996
The collection is open for research.
The Mill Creek Research Council (MCRC) is an environmental action group based in Lima Township, Washtenaw County, and was organized by Mrs. Virginia Denham. The MCRC was formed in 1964-1965 to protest a proposal by the United States Army Corps of Engineers to flood the Mill Creek area in order to provide better sewage treatment for communities downstream on the Huron River. The plan promoted by the Corps of Engineers was successfully opposed by the Research Council.
In 1965 the MCRC also organized to fight a proposal by the Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority (HCMA) to construct a 4,000-acre metropark, including a 1,500-acre lake that would be created by damming up Mill Creek. HCMA abandoned the plan in 1982, due to local opposition to condemning the land in question. HCMA was not sure if it had the power to condemn the land, and MCRC persuaded them not to investigate.
The residents remained suspicious of the HCMA, and in the early 1970s they created the South Lima Township Historical District plan. The plan's goal was to survey the township and apply for historical district status with the National Register of Historical Places. A 9,400-acre tract in Lima Township, South of I-94, was identified. The desire of the historical district council was to preserve the appearance of a 19th Century rural community in the tract.
The Michigan Department of State and the federal government determined that the tract was eligible for historical district status, and if it was registered would be the largest of its kind.
In July 1981 a proposal to preserve the tract was sent for review to the federal government, the Michigan Department of State and the National Park Service. A hearing was held by the history division of the Michigan Department of State in Lansing in April 1983. Ten people testified in favor of registration and two testified against it. The decision on the status of the historic district was then sent to the National Park Service in Washington, D.C for further investigation and approval.
A local couple, the Urquharts, who opposed the opportunity for federal intervention that registration as an historical district would allow, began an effort to block registration. They convinced a majority of 160 of 253 owners to send notarized affidavits of opposition to the government. Under the regulations, if a majority of the land/property owners in the district oppose registration, it can not be approved.
On September 8, 1983 the National Register of Historic Places reviewed the application and accidentally approved the registration. The decision was reversed in February 1984, after the mistake was revealed.
In the 1980s, the HCMA attempted to build a golf course in South Lima Township. The MCRC again prevented the action.
Subjects:
Citizens' associations--Michigan.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Historic districts--Michigan.; Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority.; Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); Lima (Mich.: Township); Mill Creek Metropark (Mich.: Proposed); Mill Creek Research Council, inc.; Sewerage--Michigan.; Washtenaw County (Mich.); Water--Michigan.; Denham, Virginia.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Barns--Michigan--Lima (Township); Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Dwellings--Michigan--Lima (Township); Farms--Michigan--Lima (Township); Fourmile Lake (Mich.); Junkyards.; Lima (Mich.: Township)--Barns.; Lima (Mich.: Township)--Dwellings.; Lima (Mich.: Township)--Farms.; Mill Creek (Mich.); Mill Creek Research Council, inc.; Mobile homes.; Sutton Lake (Mich.
Genre/Form:
Aerial photographs.; Photographs.
- U.S. Army Corps of Engineers 1965-1970
  The U.S Army Corps of Engineers series, 1965-1970 (2.2 linear feet), deals with the first dispute in the 1960s to flood the Mill Creek area to improve sewage treatment on the Huron River. The series includes correspondence, clippings, and reports and audio-tapes of meetings.
  - Original Accession
    - Administrative File
      - 1965-1970 (Box 1)
        (including annual reports and minutes)
    - Correspondence
      - Incoming
        - 1965 (Box 1)
        - 1966 (Box 1)
        - 1967 (Box 1)
        - 1968-1970 (Box 1)
      - Outgoing
        - 1965 (Box 1)
        - 1966 (Box 1)
        - 1967 (Box 1)
        - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
      - With clippings, brochures, etc
        - 1965, 3 folders (Box 1)
        - 1966, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - 1967 (Box 1)
        - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Clippings 1965-1966, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Newsletter 1965-1969 (Box 2)
    - Reports
      - Black and Veatch Consulting Report 1960 (Box 2)
      - Michigan Water Resource Commission 1957 (Box 2)
      - Student Works
        - University of Michigan Geography Study 1965 (Box 2)
        - Steinbach 1965 (Box 2)
        - Wellman thesis 1969 (Box 2)
      - Washtenaw County Water Supply and Sanitary Sewage Systems
        - Preliminary drafts (Box 2)
        - Final draft (Box 2)
      - Water Resources Study, Huron River Basin, Michigan, U.S. Health, Education and Welfare (Box 2)
      - Record of opposition 1969 (Box 2)
      - Speeches 1965-1969 (Box 2)
      - Tapes of organizational meetings 1965-1966 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - 1996 Accession
    - Clippings 1965 (Box 7)
    - Department of Interior Report 1965 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous 1965-1971 (Box 7)
- Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Association 1969-1975
  The Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Association series, 1969-1975 (3 linear feet), pertains to the dispute to create a metropark. It consists of correspondence, environmental impact statements, maps, student reports, administrative files, newsletters, newspaper articles, and topical files. After the Metropark project was abandoned, the Mill Creek Research Council continued to watch and collect material about the activities of the HCMA. Some of this material is included.
  - Original Accession
    - History (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - 1969-1970 (Box 3)
      - 1971 (Box 3)
      - 1972 (Box 3)
      - 1973 (Box 3)
    - Legislative hearing 1975 (Box 3)
    - Maps and recreational land plans (Box 3)
    - Petitions 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - Related regional recreational plans 1960-1974, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Reports
      - Environmental Impact Statement
        - 1972-1973 (Box 3)
        - 1973 Bureau of Outdoor Recreation, draft (Box 3)
        - 1974 Assessment (Box 3)
        - 1975 Report (Box 3)
        - 1975 Bureau of Outdoor Recreation, preliminary draft, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - 1975 Final draft, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - HCMA Reports
        - Biennial Reports 1973, 1975 (Box 4)
        - Detroit Five County Area Parks and Recreation Study 1973 (Box 4)
        - Hydrologic Study of the proposed Mill Creek Dam and Lake 1971 (Box 4)
      - Lima Township (Box 4)
      - Upstream Area Survey 1971 (Box 4)
      - Washtenaw County Metro Planning Commission Report 1971 (Box 4)
    - Record of Opposition 1975, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Southeast Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG) (Box 4)
    - Topical files
      - Agriculture (Box 4)
      - Area survey (Box 4)
      - Comments of individuals (Box 4)
      - Hearings (Box 5)
      - Huron River Watershed Council (Box 5)
      - Johnson, Johnson and Roy (JJR) Planning Landscape Architects (Box 5)
      - Lima Township (Box 5)
      - Michigan DNR vs. B.O.R (Box 5)
      - Michigan Legislators (Box 5)
      - Michigan United Conservation Clubs (Box 5)
      - Members (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
      - Parks and recreation (Box 5)
      - Resolutions, government units (Box 5)
      - SEMCOG (Box 5)
      - Tax data (Box 5)
      - Washington correspondence (Box 5)
      - Washtenaw County (Box 5)
      - Wayne County (Box 5)
    - Photographs (Box 5)
  - 1996 Accession
    - Administrative
      - Budgets
        - 1981 (Box 7)
        - 1988 (Box 7)
      - General undated (Box 7)
      - Minutes and Notes
        - 1971-1973 (Box 7)
        - 1977-1983 (Box 7)
    - Clippings (Box 8)
      - 1970-1971 (Box 8)
      - 1972 (Box 8)
      - 1973-1975 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence
      - 1971-1972 (Box 8)
      - 1973-1975 (Box 8)
      - 1979 (Box 8)
    - Hearings
      - 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1975 (Box 8)
    - Information Guide undated (Box 8)
    - Legislation 1973 (Box 8)
    - Reports
      - "A Plan of Water and Sewage System Development," undated (Box 8)
      - "A Report on the Problems arising from Impounded Waters," undated (Box 8)
      - "A Study of the Proposed Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority Mill Creek Park," 1971 (Box 8)
      - "Effects of the Proposed Mill Creek Park on the Chelsea School District," 1971 (Box 8)
      - HCMA Biennial Reports 1969-1971 (Box 8)
      - "Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority Mill Creek Metropark Preliminary Design Report Impoundments and Sanitary Facilities," 1974 (Box 8)
      - "Methodology for Recreation Site Evaluation," undated (Box 8)
      - "Mill Creek Water Quality Investigation," 1974 (Box 8)
      - Washtenaw County Metropolitan Planning Commission 1971 (Box 8)
    - Student Works
      - Pollard, William 1971 (Box 8)
    - Working Papers 1973 (Box 8)
- South Lima Historical District 1970-1993
  The South Lima Historical District series, 1970-1993 (3.4 linear feet), contains the research and correspondence generated as the MCRC pursued registration as an historical district. The council received several grants to perform its survey of the land and property in the township. The paperwork leading up to the grants is included, as well as the reports of findings. These reports contain comprehensive descriptions of the township and its history. The surveyors classified each property in the reports, and included many photographs, some of which are artistic in quality. The collection of photographs and surveys are well indexed, and many maps will help researchers locate the land and property in question. In order to maintain continuity, the photographs that were taken for the surveys have not been separated from the paperwork. In many cases, the negatives for pictures are included as well.
  Before the survey was conducted, the township was divided into quadrants that were labeled "A,B,C,D". Each quadrant was color-coded: yellow, red, green, blue, respectively. After the survey was completed, the farmhouses in the survey were classified according to their ability to preserve the appearance of a 19th Century rural community. The classifications were called "significant, contributing, neutral and non-contributing." These were also labeled in the report as groups "A,B,C,D", respectively.
  - Original Accession
    - Printed Materials
      - "Jerusalem Mill Area Survey of Lima Township," undated (Box 5)
      - "Lima Center Township Hall, redevelopment study," 1974, 3 folders (Box 5)
        (includes 8 architects drawings)
      - "Lima Township: a study of rural character," 1974 (Box 5)
        (includes photographs)
      - "Lima Township: general development plan report," 1972 (Box 5)
      - "Living in Lima," 1973 (Box 5)
      - "Relationships of space and land use," 1975 (Box 5)
    - Quadrant surveys
      The quadrant surveys files include a barn survey and descriptions and photographs of homes in each quadrant in the township
      - Quadrant "A" (yellow folders)
        - Barn surveys (Box 5)
        - Homes (descriptions with pictures) (Box 5)
        - Larger prints (Box 5)
      - Quadrant "B" (red folders)
        - Homes (descriptions with pictures) (Box 6)
        - Larger pictures (Box 6)
        - Report and contact prints (Box 6)
        - USGS surveys and contact prints (Box 6)
      - Quadrant "C" (green folders)
        - Larger pictures (Box 6)
        - Pictures of C-7 (Box 6)
          (coded by reel and exposure number, with some names)
        - Pictures and maps, USGS surveys (Box 6)
        - Protest to golf course (Box 6)
        - Report on preservation of C-7 (Box 6)
      - Quadrant "D" (blue folders)
        - Description of structures (includes contact sheets) (Box 6)
        - Index of properties (Box 6)
        - Larger pictures (Box 6)
    - Topical files
      - Building structure inventories with photos (Box 6)
      - Clippings
        - 1970-1985 (Box 6)
        - "Washtenaw Panorama-Lima Township," Ann Arbor News, August 15, 1956 (full page photostory on the township) (Box 6)
      - Clippings and correspondence (1970-1984) (Box 6)
      - Contact prints and negatives (mostly barn survey, turn-of-the-century reprints) (Box 6)
      - Correspondence (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, archeological survey (includes photos, slides, maps, letter of opposition) (Box 6)
      - Grant papers 1980 formally establishes link for MCRC and SLHD to share research (Box 6)
      - Michigan historic preservation grant (correspondence, application, research) (Box 6)
      - National historic register (correspondence) (Box 6)
      - Planning materials for survey of the township (Box 6)
      - Report of findings--includes "Historical Overview as related to changing landscape of Lima, 1825-1981" (Box 7)
      - Section maps (Box 7)
      - Student paper, Ina Hanel 1993 (Box 7)
      - Sutton's Lake (Box 7)
    - Township Survey 1973
      - Group A (Box 7)
      - Group B (Box 7)
      - Group C (Box 7)
      - Group D (Box 7)
    - Visual materials
      The Visual Materials files include aerial photos, photographs and negatives of homes, barns, land features, farm animals, and some people from around Lima Township.
      - Aerial shots (many have descriptions on reverse, some are indexed with negatives) (Box 7)
      - Color (3x5)
        - Church/cemetery (Box 7)
        - Farm scenes, 3 folders (Box 7)
        - Homes (Box 7)
        - Mill Creek (Box 7)
        - Sutton's Lake (Box 7)
        - Topography (Box 7)
        - 4-Mile Lake (Box 7)
      - Color (5x7)
        - Farm scenes (Box 7)
        - Homes (Box 7)
        - Mill Creek (Box 7)
      - "Ecology search" (Box 7)
        (5 boards: "A,B,C,D,S" with black and white photos and editor's notes--possibly for publication)
      - Ground shots (Box 7)
        (many are labeled and are indexed with negatives)
      - Homes (prints and negatives) (Box 7)
      - Homes, barns, farm scenes, etc. (Box 7)
        (black and white, 8x10)
      - Homes, barns, schools, etc. (black and white, 3x5) (2 boxes, 14 envelopes) (Box 7)
      - Negatives and contact prints: homes and farm scenes (Box 7)
      - Negatives: homes, and historic district map (Box 7)
      - Secretary Berglund's visit (August 21, 1979) (Box 7)
      - Turn-of-the-century: reprints, maps and drawings (prints and negatives) (Box 7)
      - USGS cards with photos (Box 7)
    - Maps
      - Lima Township, General development guideline plan, by Johnson, Johnson & Roy 1972 (Box 7)
      - Lima Township, General development guideline plan, development distribution use breakdown, by Lima Township Planning Commission 1973 (Box 7)
      - Lima Township, Historic building survey with potential historic district lines (Box 7)
      - U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, Huron River, Michigan, Mill Creek Reservoir site (Box 7)
      - Dexter SW, Michigan, topographical map 1964 (Box 7)
        (4 copies)
      - South Lima Rural Historic District, points of significance 1981 by Lynda Koch and Gerald Meyers (Box 7)
      - South Lima Rural Historic District, property lines 1981 by Lynda Koch (Box 7)
      - South Lima Rural Historic District, district boundaries/town lines 1981 by Lynda Koch (Box 7)
  - 1996 Accession
    - Background Material 1970-1973 (Box 7)
    - Clippings and Notes 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - Governor's Special Commission on Land Use Report (Interim and Final) 1972 (Box 7)
    - Grant Material
      - 1970-1972, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - 1973 (Box 7)
      - EEA 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Johnson, Johnson and Roy Plan
      - File Copy 1971-1972 (Box 7)
      - Responses 1972-1973 (Box 7)
      - Summary 1972 (Box 7)
    - Legislation (Box 7)
    - Lima Township Land Use Policy (Box 7)
- Zoning 1963-1988
  The Zoning series, 1963-1988 (.2 linear feet) contains correspondence clippings and reports about zoning ordinances and issues in Lima Township.
  - Billboards 1963-1969 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence and Clippings 1968-1988 (Box 7)
  - Green Case 1972 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous undated (Box 7)
  - Mobile Home Park Ordinance 1968-1972 (Box 9)
  - "Summary Outline of the Preliminary Draft Lima Township Zoning Ordinance," 1973, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Township Ordinances 1974 (Box 9)
- Related Organizations 1969-1987
  The Related Organizations series, 1969-1987 (.3 linear feet) contains material from other organizations in Washtenaw County that concern the Mill Creek Research Council. In some cases these organizations were affiliated with the Mill Creek Research Council. In other cases, some of the members of the Mill Creek Research Council were also prominent members of these related organizations.
  - Chelsea Area Regional Planning Committee 1972-1974 (Box 9)
  - Huron River Watershed Council (Box 9)
  - Minutes 1972-1974 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous 1972-1973 (Box 9)
  - Reports
    - "Huron River," 1976 (Box 9)
    - "Mill Creek," 1974 (Box 9)
  - Lima Township Board 1972-1987 (Box 9)
  - Southeastern Michigan Council of Governments 1973-1976 (SEMCOG), 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Washtenaw County Metropolitan Planning Commission (Box 9)
  - Comprehensive and Open Space System undated (Box 9)
  - Inventory of Recreational Lands and Facilities in Washtenaw County Michigan 1970 (Box 9)
  - Land Use Policy for Washtenaw County (Preliminary) 1976 (Box 9)
  - "Planning Prospectus," 1972-1973 (Box 9)
  - Washtenaw County Fragile Lands 1981 (Box 9)
  - Water Resources for Washtenaw County Michigan 1976 (Box 9)
- Topical Files 1964-1977
  The Topical Files series, 1964-1977 (.3 linear feet) includes some administrative material from the Mill Creek Research Council as well as reports and legislation on a number of environmental issues.
  - Administrative 1965-1966 (Box 9)
  - Economic Development Act 1972 (Box 9)
  - Legislation (Box 9)
  - 1964-1972 (Box 9)
  - 1973-1977 (Box 9)
  - Natural Rivers Program 1972 (Box 9)
  - National Cooperative Soil Survey Soils of Washtenaw County undated (Box 9)
  - Solid Waste Plans 1971-1972 (Box 9)
  - Subdivision Ordinances 1973 (Box 9)